Department of Music Records UA017
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Music Records
1889 -- 1986
circa 1830 -- 2017
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
School of Arts and Sciences
Department of Music
UA017
25.05 Linear Feet
1 Artifact(s)
This collection documents the activities and administration of the Music Department and the Music Library.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by Michael Rogan/Lilly Music Library, 2017-2018.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into six series: Administrative and office files; Programs, concerts and events; Musical scores; Faculty, staff and student files; Leo R. Lewis's piano; and Unprocessed accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of Music was established on August 7, 1895 when the Tufts College Board of Trustees voted to create a professorship in the History and Theory of Music. Professor Leo R. Lewis was appointed to the new position. Interest in music at Tufts was high from the onset. In 1896 President Capen's annual report counted 26 students enrolled in music courses - nearly 10% of Tufts' 270 students. By 1901, the Department of Music was declared "permanent" by President Capen, who lauded Professor Lewis for creating a department "likely to become one of the strongest of the College." Capen also praised Lewis for creating a chorus for the Sunday evening services in Goddard Chapel, organizing and instructing the Glee Club, preparing college songs, and "awakening an interest in music throughout the College." (Hersey, p. 32)
Tufts Music Department has always played a major role in organizing musical performances on campus. Historically, performance groups included the Glee Club, the Tufts Choir, the Banjo Club (which became the Mandolin and Guitar Club), the Jackson Glee Club, the Orchestra, the Chamber Singers, and the College Band. By 2007 Tufts Music Department had expanded its vocal and instrumental groups to include 19 performance ensembles including the Chamber Singers, Concert Choir, Tufts Jazz Orchestra (TJO), Tufts Symphony Orchestra (TSO), Wind Ensemble, and Pep Band. The Department organizes over 180 events and concerts annually.
In 1899, the Music Department found its first official home on the third floor of Goddard Gymnasium. This original space consisted of two rooms; one for general use and a second for the Music Library, which housed the collections of Rev. Thomas Wittemore, Albert Metcalf, and Frederic Louis Ritter. In 1930, the Old Chemistry Lab on Boston Avenue was converted to the "Music House." The department remained there until 1955, when it moved to the basement of the newly built Edward E. Cohen Arts Center (now Aidekman Arts Center). Outgrowing its basement facilities, the music department was relocated to 20 Professors Row, which had appropriately been home to Professor Lewis throughout his 50 year career at Tufts. In 2005 the Department found an interim home on 48 Professors Row, before making its final move to the $27 million Granoff Music Center in 2007. The Center houses the Distiler Performance Hall, the Lily Music Library, three classrooms, 20 faculty offices, and a rehearsal hall.
As of 2010, Music remains one of the largest and most active academic departments on Tufts campus, offering courses in musicology, ethnomusicology, theory, composition, and performance. Each year around 1,500 Tufts students enroll in department classes. Since 1973 a reciprocal agreement with the New England Conservatory of Music (NEC) has allowed students at both institutions to take courses at either school to be applied toward their respective degrees. Tufts also offers a five year dual-degree program with NEC, giving students the opportunity to earn their B.A. or B.S. from Tufts while earning a Bachelor of Music from NEC.
Custodial History
Some of the material was transferred from the Department of Music over the years. Some were donations by alumni and staff; the provenance of the rest of the material is unknown.
Related Materials
Glee Club Records, 1889-1951. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA. Tufts Music, 2009. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA. Sheet Music Collection, 1883-1943. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA. Roslyn Brogue Henning Papers, 1919-1996. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities and administration of the Music Department and the Music Library, as well as associated extracurricular clubs including Tufts Chorus, Glee Club, and Mandolin Club. Included are concert and event publications, musical scores, administrative scrapbooks, stock inventories, Music and Choral Library records, and correspondence of the Tufts Music Department. These materials date from 1886 to 2017. A majority of the scores and administrative files and scrapbooks document music-related activities at Tufts between 1889 and 1945, while concert and recital scrapbooks, course catalogs, and event schedules represent the activities of the department from the late 1960s to the late 1980s.
This collection also contains the personal papers and scrapbooks of Music Department faculty and staff, including Tufts professor Leo R. Lewis (1865-1945) and the Music House custodian Richard R. Lamont (d. 1972). Personal materials include correspondence, event invitations, curricula vitae, essays, reports, obituaries, course plans and curriculum outlines, biographical sketches and employment records. Also included are over 200 musical scores by beloved Tufts composers, including: Frederic Field Bullard, Elliot Wright Haynes, Leo Rich Lewis, Carrie Bullard Lewis and Elbridge Ward Newton.
Tufts University -- History; Tufts University. Department of Music.; Music and musical performances; Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work
- Administrative and office files, 1899 -- 1988; UA017.001; 5.3 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains administrative scrapbooks, ledgers, office records, and course catalogs from 1899 to 1988. Early department records were kept in the form of scrapbooks. Office scrapbooks contain department correspondence, faculty and staff to-do lists, course outlines and assignments, and financial records and receipts. There are also scrapbooks that describe, index and inventory the Music House Library, and one that functions as an inventory for the stock room. Some scrapbooks also organize articles about prominent composers and musicians, and were probably used as Music Library resources. Folders of administrative records include correspondence, explanations and essays on the organization system used in the Choral Library, a collection of catalogs describing the Bowen Chimes, information on the publication of Rev. Harry Adam Hersey's "A History of Music in Tufts College, 1856-1945," documentation of the 1973 agreement to create a joint program with the New England Conservatory, and in-depth catalogs of course descriptions from 1983 to 1988. Some administrative correspondence, course notes, and department information from the period between 1894 and 1945 can also be found in the personal files and scrapbooks of Leo R. Lewis in Series IV: Faculty, staff and students.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - [Music library and office files], 1899 -- 1904; UA017.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
    This scrapbook contains information regarding Music Department courses as well as write-ups on books about music. This scrapbook also contains a plan for the Music Department building at this time.
  - [Choral administrative and library records], 1899 -- 1935; UA017.001.010.00002 (Box 10)
    This scrapbook contains information regarding Tufts Chorus, including correspondence, bills, rosters and memorandums to choir members. This scrapbook also contains a document titled, "Permanent Organization of the College Choir," which includes organizational information about the choir from 1900. The back of this scrapbook seems to contain a choral index with Tufts-related music and the pieces' corresponding Choral Library Index number.
  - General index, 1904 -- 1909; UA017.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
    This scrapbook contains the index to the Choral Library. Tufts-related compositions and event programs are glued into the pages and labeled with their corresponding index number.
  - Tufts music [Office files], 1909 -- 1944; UA017.001.011.00002 (Box 11)
    This scrapbook contains bills and receipts from engravers, printers, and book binders, as well as correspondence with service providers. Bills include information on the title and length of musical pieces that went to print as well as the cost for the services provided. Music department graphics and logos used on published music are also included in this scrapbook.
  - Scrapbook 1943-1944, 1909 -- 1945; UA017.001.011.00003 (Box 11)
    The front half of this scrapbook contains a couple of newspaper articles and a few programs from concerts and events from 1943-1945. Most materials are not affixed to the pages and a majority of the book is empty. The back half of this scrapbook dates from 1909-1911 and contains what appears to be course material. It seems to be preparation for a class with 59 different assignments. Many of these assignments seems to have had corresponding musical pieces, but these pieces have been removed.
  - RRL Vol. I Scrapbook - Office data, 1938 -- 1939; UA017.001.012.00001 (Box Shared 44)
    This scrapbook contains correspondence, to-do lists, library information, concert plans, and course information. RRL is assumed to be Richard Roy Lamont, the "Custodian" of the Music House at this time.
  - RRL Vol. II Scrapbook - Office data, 1939 -- 1940; UA017.001.012.00002 (Box Shared 44)
  - Stock Miscellany from and in Choral Library in Music House, 1938 -- 1940; UA017.001.013.00001 (Box data_value_missing_b4733843f3b614d1631b54200ceb4753)
    This scrapbook contains programs for events and information on stock of published music and pamphlets. Each musical piece and/or program has a corresponding number, probably corresponding to its location in the Choral Library.
  - Stock Miscellany from and in Choral Library in Music House, 1938 -- 1944; UA017.001.014.00001 (Box data_value_missing_b4733843f3b614d1631b54200ceb4753)
    This scrapbook contains newspaper clippings about musical matters, articles about composers and musicians, and portraits of composers and musicians. It also contains clippings of reviews on books written about music and composers.
  - [Explanation of numbering system for Tufts College Series publications], 1921; UA017.001.015.00001 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
  - [Bowen Chimes Information], 1924 -- 1926; UA017.001.015.00002 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
  - [Music House files], 1936 -- 1939; UA017.001.015.00003 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
  - [Music House files], 1940 -- 1946; UA017.001.015.00004 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
  - History of Tufts Music, 1946 -- 1947; UA017.001.015.00005 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
    This folder contains information on Rev. Adams Hersey's book on Tufts Music.
  - New England Conservatory of Music, 1978; UA017.001.015.00006 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
    This folder contains the original agreement between NEC and Tufts University as well as early descriptions of the program.
  - Music course descriptions, 1983 -- 1985; UA017.001.015.00007 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
  - Music course descriptions, 1986 -- 1988; UA017.001.015.00008 (Box UA017 Shared 1)
- Concerts, recitals and events, 1886 -- 2018; 1954 -- 1993; UA017.002; 6.6 Linear Feet
  This series includes programs, newspaper clippings, calendars and photographs from Music Department concerts, recitals, and events that took place between 1886 and 2017. The majority of this series is composed of scrapbooks containing programs and clippings. Scrapbooks represent the events hosted by the department from 1972 until 1986. There is also an earlier scrapbook from the academic year 1952-53 and a bound catalog of 1991-92 events. Individual programs from 1886 to 1984 were also found in boxes of musical scores and were added to this series. These include programs from Tufts Night at the Pops in 1901 and 1941. This series also contains ten photographs from the 1901 musical performance of Milton's Comus. Music from this performance can be found in Series III: Musical scores.
  - [Concert and event programs], 1954 -- 1955; UA017.002.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Department of Music recitals and concerts, 1972 -- 1973; UA017.002.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Department of Music recitals and concerts, 1973 -- 1974; UA017.002.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Music Department Recitals, 1974 -- 1975; UA017.002.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Tufts University Department of Music, 1975 -- 1976; UA017.002.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Tufts University Department of Music concerts and recitals, 1976 -- 1977; UA017.002.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - At Tufts, 1977-06 -- 1978; UA017.002.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Tufts University Department of Music concerts and recitals, 1978 -- 1979; UA017.002.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Music Department, 1979 -- 1980; UA017.002.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University Department of Music Concert Series, 1980 -- 1981; UA017.002.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University Department of Music Concert Series, 1981 -- 1982; UA017.002.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Music Department, 1982 -- 1983; UA017.002.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Tufts Music Department scrapbook, 1983 -- 1984; UA017.002.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University Department of Music, 1984 -- 1985; UA017.002.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Events in music, 1985 -- 1986; UA017.002.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Concert programs, 1886 -- 1941; UA017.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
    This folder contains programs from Tufts musical concerts, as well as a program from Tufts Night at the Pops from 1941.
  - [Tufts Night at the Pops original program], 1901; UA017.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
    Note on folder reads: Tufts night at the Pops - Original Program. First one- May 29, 1901.
  - [Photographs of 1901 production of Milton's Comus], UA017.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
    This folder contains ten photographs and a list of scenes depicted in the images.
  - [Concert Programs], 1967 -- 1984; UA017.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Tufts University Department of Music Concert Programs, 1991 -- 1992; UA017.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
    A bound collection of concert programs.
  - Tisch Rooftop Cafe Program, 2002; UA017.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Concert in Honor of Vivian Taylor, 2006; UA017.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Concert and event program, 2007; UA017.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Concert and event programs, 2007 -- 2008; UA017.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - [Programs and events calendar], 2008; UA017.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Concert and event programs, 2011; UA017.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - CommunityMusic@Tufts classes for young musicians and adults, 2014; UA017.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Louis Armstrong Ivy Weekend concert (1 of 2), 1958-05-03; UA017.002.018 (Box data_value_missing_464b2eedf7bede247ed3c50e1ce5ff59, Box 18)
    Audio reel recording of Louis Armstrong playing Ivy Weekend concert, May 3, 1958. Reel 1 of 2.
    Side A run time: 43:29. Side B run time: 38:45.
  - Louis Armstrong Ivy Weekend concert (2 of 2), 1958-05-03; UA017.002.019 (Box data_value_missing_464b2eedf7bede247ed3c50e1ce5ff59, Box 19)
    Audio reel recording of Louis Armstrong playing Ivy Weekend concert, May 3, 1958. Reel 2 of 2.
    Side A run time: 44:12. Side A note: "Final part of concert." Side B note: "Only music - not part of concert."
  - Events and Community Music Calendar, Fall, 2016; UA017.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Concert and Event Programs, circa 1955 -- 1989; UA017.002.003.00014 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Transferred by Michael Rogan (Head of Lilly Music Library), 2017, accession UA-2017-047.
  - Concert and Event Programs, circa 2008 -- 2018; UA017.002.003.00015 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Musical scores, 1880 -- 1970; UA017.003; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains songbooks, prompt books, and approximately 220 scores dating from 1880 to 1970. Most of the scores were originally housed in the Music House Choral Library and still carry their library index number. A majority of the scores were composed or arranged by Tufts faculty, staff, and students and deal with Tufts-related subjects. Represented are class songs and odes, pep songs, marches, songs celebrating Jumbo, and songs describing life on "The Hill." Many of the pieces were also performed Tufts Glee Club, Tufts Chorus, Tufts Mandolin Club and similar student organizations. The composers represented include Leo R. Lewis A1887 H1922, Richard R. Lamont A1911, Fredric F. Bullard, Philip B. Lewis A1922, Willis A. Moore A1898, Joseph W. Morton A1911, Alton T. Williams A1920, M. H. Merrell A1896, William A. Johnson A1936, and Nowell Ingalls A1900. Also included are published collections of Tufts songbooks from 1895 to 1950. Glee Club prompt books containing scripts and song lyrics from performances in 1905, 1906 and 1907 are also present.
  This series is arranged alphabetically according to song title.
  - 27 Bells, 1898 -- 1930; UA017.003.004.00001 (Box 4)
    This piece is also referred to as "24 Bells."
    score
  - 1918 Song, 1928; UA017.003.004.00002 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder was written for the 10th Reunion of the Class of 1918.
  - A capella reprints, 1936; UA017.003.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Alma mater (for male voices), 1920; UA017.003.004.00004 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder arranged by R. R. Lamont for the Tufts College Glee Club. Words by W. H. Moore.
  - Alma mater's day, 1916 -- 1921; UA017.003.004.00005 (Box 4)
    Music of piece in folder by E. W. Hayes for the Class of 1916.
  - The American Flag, 1942 -- 1945; UA017.003.004.00006 (Box 4)
    Music of piece in folder by C. B. Lewis. Score for full orchestra by L. R. Lewis. Text by J. R. Drake.
  - Amor Triumphans (The Boat of Love) [Piano and Orchestra Scores], 1940; UA017.003.004.00007 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder edited by L. R. Lewis. Music by F. F. Bullard. Poem by R. A. Cram. Score for Soli and Chorus by W. H. Howard and R. R. Lamont.
  - And in the sixth month, 1902; UA017.003.004.00008 (Box 4)
    Composed by E. Cutter, Jr. Gift of composer to R. R. Lamont.
  - Around the Rez, 1906; UA017.003.004.00009 (Box 4)
    Composed by M. N. Dustin, '06. Mandolin Club Score.
  - At the End of the Day Give a Cheer, 1911 -- 1923; UA017.003.004.00010 (Box 4)
    Music by R. R. Lamont. Text by R. Hovey.
  - The Bay State Song of Massachusetts, 1931; UA017.003.004.00011 (Box 4)
    Music and text of piece in folder by R. R. Lamont.
  - Beam From Yonder Star, 1896; UA017.003.004.00012 (Box 4)
    Music by F. F. Bullard. Text by W. P. Foster.
  - Bible Stories, 1914; UA017.003.004.00013 (Box 4)
    Remembered by McJannet '16.
  - The Bridal Rose, 1886 -- 1920; UA017.003.004.00014 (Box 4)
    Arr. by C. B. Claus. Music by C. Lavallee.
  - The Brown and Blue, 1901 -- 1905; UA017.003.004.00015 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder composed by E. W. Newton.
  - Brown and Blue Forever, 1923; UA017.003.004.00016 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder arranged by L. R. Lewis. Music by N. W. Morison. Text by E. A. Terhune, Jr.
  - The Building of the Ship, 1913; UA017.003.004.00017 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder composed by H. Lahee. Words by H. W. Longfellow.
  - Campus Dreams Waltz, 1924; UA017.003.004.00018 (Box 4)
    Composed by E. W. Blake.
  - Campus song, 1939; UA017.003.004.00019 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder composed by F. F. Bullard. Some scores refer to this song as "The Stein Song."
  - The Captain's Yarns, 1911; UA017.003.004.00020 (Box 4)
    Remembered by Tosi.
  - The Captivity, 1938; UA017.003.004.00021 (Box 4)
    Composed by C. B. Lewis.
  - Carmena, 1909 -- 1910; UA017.003.004.00022 (Box 4)
    Piece in folder arranged by H. L. Wilson for Glee and Mandolin Club.
  - Carols arranged for three trumpets, 1941 -- 1943; UA017.003.004.00023 (Box 4)
    Piece contained in folder arranged by R. R. Lamont and L. R. Lewis.
  - Casey Jones, 1930; UA017.003.004.00024 (Box 4)
    Piece contained in folder arranged by L. R. Lewis. Composed by E. Newton.
  - Chanson Indoue, 1931; UA017.003.004.00025 (Box 4)
    Piece contained in folder arranged by R. Kasakov.
  - Charlie's Light - Hymn to College Hill, 1900 -- 1940; UA017.003.004.00026 (Box 4)
  - Charlie Tufts His College, 1943; UA017.003.004.00027 (Box 4)
    Charlie Tufts His College arranged by L. R. Lewis. Composed by C. B. Lewis.
  - Charlie Tufts His College and For Tufts Hurrah!, 1943; UA017.003.004.00028 (Box 4)
    Charlie Tufts His College arranged by L. R. Lewis. Composed by C. B. Lewis. For Tufts Hurrah! composed by L. R. Lewis.
  - Class Day, 1920 -- 1936; UA017.003.004.00029 (Box 4)
    Composed by L. R. Lewis.
  - Class Ode 1898, UA017.003.004.00030 (Box 4)
    The piece in the folder was composed by W. A. Moore.
  - Class Ode 1901, UA017.003.004.00031 (Box 4)
  - Class Song 1903, UA017.003.004.00032 (Box 4)
  - Class Song of 1931, UA017.003.004.00033 (Box 4)
    The piece in this folder was composed by T. Laminan. Words by K. MacKinnon.
  - Class Song of 1938, UA017.003.004.00034 (Box 4)
    The piece in this folder was composed by W. A. Johnson.
  - The College Hero - A musical extravaganza, 1908; UA017.003.004.00035 (Box 4)
    Libretto and lyrics by W. Davis. Music by J. M. Duganne and W. Davis.
  - Come o'er the Sea, 1911; UA017.003.004.00036 (Box 4)
    Composed by F. F. Bullard. Lyrics by T. Moore.
  - Comus [Songs and instrumental], 1901; UA017.003.004.00037 (Box 4)
    The parts in this folder were arranged by L. R. Lewis. Music by H. Lawes.
  - The Songs of Comus, 1901; UA017.003.004.00038 (Box 4)
    Arranged by L. R. Lewis. Music by H. Lawes.
  - Concertino for Trumpet, 1900 -- 1930; UA017.003.004.00039 (Box 4)
    The parts in this folder were composed by L. R. Lewis.
  - Concert Overture (Concert Ouverture) - A very early work, 1909; UA017.003.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Concert Overture, 1909; UA017.003.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Concert Overture [Orchestra score], 1909; UA017.003.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - The Consolation of Music (Trost der Musik), 1909 -- 1941; UA017.003.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Conundrum Song, 1930; UA017.003.005.00005 (Box 5)
    Remembered by W. M. Watson
  - Dear Alma Mater, 1898 -- 1935; UA017.003.005.00006 (Box 5)
    The piece in this folder was composed by L. R. Lewis.
  - Doan Ye Cry, Ma Honey, 1913; UA017.003.005.00007 (Box 5)
    The piece in this folder was arranged by F. J. Smith. Words and music by A. W. Noll.
  - The Eighth Psalm, 1920; UA017.003.005.00008 (Box 5)
    The piece in this folder was composed by F. F. Bullard.
  - Excalibur: Symphonic Poem, 1920 -- 1940; UA017.003.005.00009 (Box 5)
    Folder states that the piece was composed by L. A. Coerne and submitted anonymously in a competition.
  - The Fern Song, 1908; UA017.003.005.00010 (Box 5)
    Composed by F. F. Bullard. Words by J. B. Tabb.
  - Festival Overture, 1888; UA017.003.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - [F. F. Bullard - scores and compositions], 1888 -- 1938; UA017.003.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Fight! Tufts, Fight!, 1914; UA017.003.005.00013 (Box 5)
    Composed by E. W. Hayes
  - First String Quartet in A-minor., 1897; UA017.003.005.00014 (Box 5)
    Composed by F. F. Bullard.
  - The Flag That Makes Us One - A-flat, 1918 -- 1928; UA017.003.005.00015 (Box 5)
    Music by L. R. Lewis. Text by F. H. Sykes.
  - The Flag That Makes Us One - F, 1918 -- 1928; UA017.003.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - A Footlight Fancy, 1913; UA017.003.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - A Footlight Fancy, 1901; UA017.003.005.00018 (Box 5)
    Arranged by Ingalls for Mandolin Club.
  - Forward, 1940; UA017.003.005.00019 (Box 5)